Jones, Louis C.; Papers ua902.004
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Louis C. Jones Papers
1936
1941-1945
1947-1949
1954-1978
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Jones, Louis C. (Louis Clark), 1908-1990
ua902.004
1 cubic ft.
The Louis C. Jones Papers consist primarily of the circular letters sent by Jones during World War II to former students of the State Teachers College and replies to these letters from service men and women. Jones was employed by the New York State College for Teachers, first as an Instructor (1934-42) and later as an Associate Professor of English (1942-46).
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Louis C. Jones initially donated his papers to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Biographical Sketch
Louis C. Jones was born in Albany, New York, on June 28, 1908. He received a B.A. in English from Hamilton College in 1930 and an L.H.D. in 1962. Jones obtained his master's degree in 1931 and a Ph.D. in 1941, both from Columbia University. Jones began his teaching career as an Instructor of English at Long University (1931-32) and at Syracuse University (1933-34). Jones was employed by the New York State College for Teachers, first as an Instructor (1934-42) and later as an Associate Professor of English (1942-46). In 1946 Jones was appointed Executive Director of the New York State Historical Association and Farmers Museum in Cooperstown, New York. Jones also served as a professor and director of the Cooperstown graduate program of the State University of New York at Oneonta. Jones was fascinated with folklore and ghostlore. This interest led Jones to publish Spooks of the Valley (1948) and Things That Go Bump in the Night (1959). The latter emphasizes the traditional folklore about ghosts and ghost hauntings in New York State.
Scope and Contents
The Louis C. Jones Papers consist primarily of the circular letters sent by Jones during World War II to former students of the State Teachers College and replies to these letters from service men and women.[1] The primary focus of this correspondence was the activities of former students, but interspersed in the letters are comments about social conditions at home and abroad and a few observation about combat conditions. The papers contain numerous photographs of serving personnel. The papers also contain a sampling of Jones' publications, primarily relating to New York folklore and specifically to ghostlore. Four of the circular letters written by Jones were transcribed for the University at Albany Veterans Project. The letters dated October 9, 1943; February 11, 1944; April 28, 1944; and March 14, 1945 are availalbe online. The New York State Historical Association holds the Louis C. Jones Folklore Archives in the Special Collections Department of its Research Library. It contains materials collected by Jones' students in American Folklore at the New York State College for Teachers. Related manuscript collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives can be found in the University Archives, Folklore subject page, and Military and Armed Conflict subject page.
1. In 1943, Jones took over the task of corresponding with State College service personnel from Dr. D. V. Smith who had left State College to assume the presidency of Cortland State Teachers' College. State College News, September 24, 1943, p. 3.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 is arranged alphabetically by subject while Series 2 is arranged chronologically, by publication.
Military and Armed Conflict; Folklore; Folklore; World War II; Educators; Albany County (N.Y.); Publications; Clippings; Correspondence; Files by subject; UAlbany Faculty & Alumni Papers; Jones, Louis C.; State College for Teachers (Albany, N.Y.)
- World War I Correspondence, 1936; 1941-1945; 1947-1949; 1954-1978; 1; 0.9 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists mainly of letters and postcards. Also included are some war department press releases, newspaper clippings and photographs of former students of the New York State College for Teachers at Albany who were serving in the armed services. The papers also contain a card index listing the names and service addresses of all former State College students serving in the armed services from 1941 to 1945. Though for the most part the files contain correspondence relating to the activities of fellow students, they also include observations about fellow servicemen from the greater Albany area and about the social conditions where the correspondents were stationed. There are few observations about combat conditions.
  - Jones' circular letters to service personnel, 1943-1945 (Box 1 (1-World War I Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - Letters to Jones from former students of the State Teachers College at Albany, 1942-1945 (Box 1 (1-World War I Correspondence), Folder 2-22)
  - Letters (unidentified) to Jones, 1942-1945 (Box 1 (1-World War I Correspondence), Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous war transmittals, 1945 (Box 1 (1-World War I Correspondence), Folder 24)
  - Photos (identified) of State students in service, 1942-1945 (Box 1 (1-World War I Correspondence), Folder 25)
  - Photos (unidentified) of State students in service, 1942-1945 (Box 1 (1-World War I Correspondence), Folder 26)
  - Personal correspondence to Louis C. Jones, 1944 (Box 1 (1-World War I Correspondence), Folder 27)
  - Military public relation releases, 1944-1945 (Box 1 (1-World War I Correspondence), Folder 28)
  - List of students in military service with obituaries, 1941 August-1945 May (Box 1 (1-World War I Correspondence), Folder 29)
  - Card index to file of former State students serving in World War II, 1942-1945 (Box 1 (1-World War I Correspondence), Folder 30)
- Publications, 1936-1978; 2; 0.1 cubic ft.
  Arranged chronologically by publication year.
  This series contains press releases associated with Louis C. Jones' career as well as drafts and off prints of his works on folklore. The publications and press releases were taken from the University Archives Faculty Vertical File and relate to Jones' career and his interest in folklore.
  - The Berlin Murder Case in Folklore and Ballad, 1936 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 31)
  - Bill Greenfield: A Nearly Forgotten Hero, 1936 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 32)
  - The College Research Paper, 1936 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 33)
  - Structural Charts of Great Dramas, 1936 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 34)
  - Paul Bunyan is Back, 1941 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 35)
  - Hitchhiking Ghosts in New York, 1944 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 36)
  - The Ghosts of New York: An Analytical Study, 1944 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 37)
  - Spooks of the Valley (first draft), 1947-1948 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 38)
  - Practitioners of Folk Medicine, 1949 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 39)
  - A Long Look Over My Left Shoulder, 1965 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 40)
  - The Crime and Punishment of Stephen Arnold, 1966 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 41)
  - Press releases on Jones, 1954-1978 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 42)